Finding Aid for Dept. of Ophthalmology (University of Michigan) records 1951-2003 (bulk 1968-1990)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Ophthalmology (University of Michigan) records 1951-2003 1968-1990
University of Michigan. Dept. of Ophthalmology.
The Department of Ophthalmology is a teaching and research unit of the University of Michigan Medical School. Records include chairman's topical file relating to the administration and programs of the department. The majority of the documentation is from the tenure of Paul R. Lichter, although the tenures of John Henderson and Bruce Fralick are also represented. Documentation relates to the administration and programs of the department, and the construction of the W.K. Kellogg Eye Center.
956 Bimu C46 2
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (Donor no. 8052 ) was first received in 1994. Periodic accessions are expected. Additional material was received from Paul R. Lichter (Donor no. 7979 ) in 2007
The collection is open for research.
The first chairman of the Department of Ophthalmology, George E. Frothingham came to Ann Arbor in 1867 to serve as prosector of Surgery and assistant demonstrator of Anatomy. On March 29, 1870 the University of Michigan Board of Regents appointed Frothingham to the newly created position of lecturer in Ophthalmology. Two years later, the dean of the Medical School recommended that Frothingham be promoted to professorial status. Formal approval of a new position, Professor of Ophthalmology and Aural Surgery, was granted by the Regents on June 25, 1872. With this appointment, the University of Michigan was effectively establishing a new department, only the third department of ophthalmology constituted in an American school of medicine.
The department flourished during Frothingham's tenure. In 1878 alone, 33 cataract operations were performed at University Hospital constituting 55% of all surgical operations. At this time 90-95% of surgical operations performed on the eye were for cataracts. The demand for service was sufficient to warrant the addition of an eye and ear ward at the hospital in 1881 at a cost of $2500. This was the first such medical unit within an academic institution. The curriculum was formalized in 1880 to include three classes in ophthalmology: eye and ear clinic, ophthalmology and otology, and clinical ophthalmology.
Frothingham left the department in 1889 following an acrimonious, highly publicized debate within the Medical School over proposals to move the university's clinical facilities to Detroit. Frothingham vigorously supported the initiative. The inability to secure adequate supplies in Ann Arbor formed the basis of the argument in favor of relocation. One proponent of the plan declared, "One might as well undertake to raise oranges in Canada as to have a complete clinic in Ann Arbor." The proposal was ultimately defeated and Frothingham was replaced by Fleming Carrow in 1889.
The most significant development within the department under Carrow was the appointment of an assistant to help with ophthalmic education. This addition to the staff was prompted by the shift to a four-year program in medicine during the 1891 academic year. The 1890s also encompassed the first attempts at postgraduate education on the part of the ophthalmic faculty. Carrow eventually resigned over a dispute with the Board of Regents concerning restrictions on private practice for university faculty. He was subsequently instrumental in the founding of St. Joseph Mercy Hospital.
In 1904 instruction in Ophthalmic and Aural Surgery was formally split to create one department for complaints of the eye and another to handle conditions of the ear, nose and throat. In 1910, an eye and ear hospital was completed on Catherine Street to meet the needs of these departments. Both departments were subsequently moved to quarters in the university hospital in 1926. This period witnessed the development of the "Michigan Rotation System" by Walter R. Parker whereby students in Ophthalmology would spend their first year of residency in the general hospital followed by three years of specialization in ophthalmic practice. This system proved popular and was replicated in other institutions.
This program reflected an emphasis on clinical service in the department. A focus on the clinical aspects of the program was given greater immediacy through the need for patient income. High fixed costs and emphasis on subspecialization in research required a constant base of financial support.
Following the shortage of students engendered by World War II, the Department of Ophthalmology embarked on a period of sustained growth. The number of residents rose from 6 in 1940 to 21 in 1975. By 1975, the department treated 28,000 patients annually. During the same period, the professional staff increased from 3 to 12 members. This growth resulted in a continual need for larger facilities. In 1952 the department moved to the University Hospital Outpatient Building. In 1970 several units within the department were relocated to the Parkview medical facility. Tensions resulting from the dispersion of various ophthalmic activities were resolved with the centralization of all ophthalmic services in the Parkview-Turner Hospital as approved by a Regents action request dated January 18, 1979.
Departmental growth was accompanied by an increasing emphasis on clinical service within the Department of Ophthalmology. Clinical aspects of the program were extended due to the mounting need for patient income. High fixed costs and an emphasis on specialization in research required a constant base of supplemental financial support.
Paul R. Lichter became chair of the Department of Ophthalmology in 1978. Lichter, a Michigan native, received his B.A. and M.D. from the University of Michigan in 1960 and 1964 respectively. He took his residency at the University of Michigan Hospital. In 1971 he became an assistant professor of ophthalmology at the University of Michigan. He became a full professor in 1978, the same year he was appointed as department chair. Lichter's primary research interests are management of glaucoma and cataract, intraocular lens implantation, anterior segment tumors, and management of glaucoma in infants and children.
One of Lichter's prime objectives as chairman was to consolidate the department, which, over the years had come to reside in several different buildings. As chair, Lichter was instrumental in the planning and construction of the W.K. Kellogg Eye Center.
Funding for the remodeling and expansion of the Parkview-Turner space was secured through a fund drive intended to raise ten million dollars for the department. A 1981 grant of four million dollars from the Kellogg Foundation insured the success of the program. The fund drive was completed in 1983 and ophthalmic facilities were renamed the W. K. Kellogg Eye Center in honor of the significant contributions of the Kellogg Foundation. The last phase in the establishment of the eye center was realized in 1985 with erection of an education and residency building for the Department of Ophthalmology. An addition
In May 2006, the Board of Regents approved a $121 million expansion to the eye center intended to make it the largest and most comprehensive eye center in the Midwest. The 222,000 square-foot building project was named the Delores S. and William K. Brehm Center for Type 1 Diabetes Research and Study. The Brehm Center was dedicated in 2010.
Paul Lichter stepped down as chairman in 2012
Chairmen of the Department of Ophthalmology (1872- )
1872-1889 Dr. George E. Frothingham
1889-1904 Dr. Fleming Carrow
1904-1932 Dr. Walter R. Parker
1932-1933 Dr. George Slocum
1933-1968 Dr. F. Bruce Fralick
1968-1978 Dr. John W. Henderson
1978-2012 Dr. Paul R. Lichter
The records of the University of Michigan Department of Ophthalmology were received in two separate accessions. The first accession, received in 1994, is located in box 1. The materials received from chairman Paul R. Lichter in 2007 are located in boxes 2-5. The records of the University of Michigan Department of Ophthalmology, consisting of 5 linear feet, are organized into two topical series: Chairman's Topical Files, 1951-1981 and Paul R. Lichter Topical Files, 1978-2003.
Subjects:
Medicine--Michigan.; Ophthalmology--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Ophthalmology.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. W. K. Kellogg Eye Center.; University of Michigan. W. K. Kellogg Eye Center.
Genre Terms:
Pamphlets.; Directories.; Proposals.; Reports.
- Chairman's Topical Files 1951-1981
  The bulk of the records in the Chairman's Topical Files, 1951-1981 date from the chairmanship of John W. Henderson (1968-1978). The records describe programs, facilities, and affiliated clinics and hospitals. Significant programs represented in the records include the External Disease Service, Lens Dispensary, Low Vision Clinic, Michigan Lions Eye Bank, and Parkview-Retina Service.
  Materials on the renovation of Parkview and the design of the Turner addition including floor plans are located in the Outpatient Clinic, Parkview Planning (1977-1978) and Parkview Relocation (1973-1978) files.
  Records documenting the department's affiliation with various hospitals and regional facilities include Ford Hospital, Milan Federal Prison, Plymouth State Home and Training Center, Veterans Administration Hospital, Wayne County General Hospital, and Ypsilanti Regional Hospital.
  An especially rich source for information relating to glaucoma can be found in the research papers of Harold Falls (1955-1972). Additional research related materials are located in the Thursday Morning Conference folder (1972-1977).
  The Paul R. Lichter Topical Files, 1978-2003 document Lichter's tenure as chair of the Department of Ophthalmology. It richly details Lichter's involvement with the construction of the W.K. Kellogg Eye Center, his chairmanship of the department and touches upon his stint as editor-in -chief of Ophthalmology, the Journal of the American Academy of Ophthalmology. The Lichter series includes three subseries: Administration, Personal Files, and W.K. Kellogg Eye Center.
  The Administration files documents the organization and operations of the Department of Ophthalmology. The files includes annual reports which review the performance of the department and its faculty, meeting minutes from faculty retreats, and departmental review and strategic planning reports.
  The Daniel G. Green Retirement Dinner and Book of Remembrances, 2003 folder includes photographs of Green's retirement party as well as a CD with photographs of the party. Green is a Professor Emeritus in the departments of Ophthalmology and Biomedical Engineering. His research interests include retinal physiology of visual adaptation and transgenic mice.
  The Photographs folder includes pictures of doctors in the department of ophthalmology as well as architectural proofs of the W.K. Kellogg Eye Center
  - Academic Evaluation and Planning Project 1976 (Box 1)
  - American Orthoptic Council 1951-1962 (Box 1)
  - Chief of Service 1975 (Box 1)
  - CAA-Clinical Phase Committee 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Community Medicine Program 1972 (Box 1)
  - Conference Schedule 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Degrees Granted, Master of Science in Ophthalmology 1935-1981 (Box 1)
  - Department Promotion 1977 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Reviews 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Educational Space Study 1979 (Box 1)
  - Electro-Diagnostic Lab 1975 (Box 1)
  - Emergency Room Inter-Disciplinary Committee 1977 (Box 1)
  - External Disease Service 1970-1977
    - Corneal Disease Program 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Contact Lens Service 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - Parke Davis-ARA-A Study 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Corneal Cryopreservation 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Falls, Harold-Research Papers 1955, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Ford Hospital 1973-1977 (Box 1)
  - Glaucoma 1972-1975
    - General 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    - Tonometry Program 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Hospital Administration-University Hospital Replacement 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Hospital Rent 1980 (Box 1)
  - Inpatient Clinic 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Integrated Flexible Medical-Premedical Program 1971, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Laser Safety Eye Exam 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Learning Disability Program 1975 (Box 1)
  - Lens Dispensary 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Low Vision Clinic 1973-1978 (Box 1)
  - Malpractice Insurance 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Medical Education 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Lions Eye Bank 1968-1978 (Box 1)
  - Milan Federal Prison 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Oculoplasty Clinic 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Operating Rooms 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Ophthalmology Residents 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Ophthalmology Research Laboratory 1969-1978 (Box 1)
  - Optometry, Proposed School of 1971-1976
    - Optometry School Committee 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - School of Optometry 1971-1976 (Box 1)
  - Orthoptics 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Outpatient Clinic 1972-1978
    - Charges 1974-1978 (Box 1)
    - General 1972-1978 (Box 1)
    - Personnel 1972 (Box 1)
    - Parkview Planning 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Parkview Relocation 1973-1978 (Box 1)
    - Eye Institute 1977 (Box 1)
    - Planning 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - Parkview 1970-1979
    - General 1970-1979 (Box 1)
    - Operating Room 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    - Equipment 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    - Retina Service 1971-1977 (Box 1)
    - Turner Addition 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Photography 1971-1977 (Box 1)
  - Plymouth State Home and Training Center 1971-1977 (Box 1)
  - Postgraduate Medicine 1969-1978
    - General 1975-1978 (Box 1)
    - Ophthalmology Staff Participation in Programs of Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine 1969-1973 (Box 1)
    - Continuing Education Committee of Michigan Academy of General Practice 1971 (Box 1)
    - Ophthalmology, Future Meetings 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    - Visiting Professors 1969 (Box 1)
  - Professional Standards Review Organization 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Staff By-Laws Undated (Box 1)
  - Surgical Advisory Committee 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - Thursday Morning Conference 1972-1977 (Box 1)
  - Ultrasound 1970-1977
    - General 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Ultrasonography Conference 1973, 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - American Institute of Ultrasonics in Medicine October 15-18, 1973, 1971 (Box 1)
  - University Hospital Organization 1970 (Box 1)
  - Veterans Administration Hospital 1971-1978 (Box 1)
  - Wayne County General Hospital 1970-1978
    - Dr. Danielski 1978 (Box 1)
    - New Position 1970-1974 (Box 1)
  - Ypsilanti Regional Psychiatric Hospital 1975-1979 (Box 1)
- Paul R. Lichter Topical Files 1978-2003
  The Paul Lichter Personal Files include correspondence from Lichter's stint as editor-in-chief of Ophthalmology. The files also include correspondence regarding his visits to the Cullen Eye Institute at Baylor University and the Jules Stein Eye Institute
  to observe the operations of eye centers which would help in planning the W. K. Kellogg Eye Center.
  The W.K. Kellogg Eye Center materials comprise the bulk of the Lichter series. The records document the planning, fundraising, construction, dedication and the operation of the Eye Center. The W.K. Kellogg Eye Center files include planning, fundraising, construction, and dedication. Planning records include architectural and functional space plans, construction plans and proposals, and reports. Fundraising materials include cost figures, a fundraising brochure, and letters seeking support. Construction documents include the Certificate of Need, copies of grant applications and support materials, and meeting minutes. Dedication materials include correspondence regarding Alumni Day and the Dedication of the Eye Center in 1985, as well as miscellaneous Eye Center Dedication day material. Included among the material is a folder on Bradley R. Straatsma. The folder contains correspondence regarding Straatsma's nomination for an honorary degree in conjunction with the dedication ceremony and a copy of Straatsma's address at the Eye Center dedication.
  - Administration
    - Annual Reports
      - Background 1967-1978 (includes chairman search material) (Box 2)
      - 1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980 (Box 2)
      - 1981 (Box 2)
      - 1982 (Box 2)
      - 1983 (Box 2)
      - 1984 (Box 2)
      - 1985 (Box 2)
      - 1986 (Box 2)
      - 1987 (Box 2)
        (includes summaries and highlights from 1967, 1971-1986)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
      - 1992 (Box 2)
      - Annual Faculty Reports 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Budget 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Chairman Search Background 1978 (Box 2)
    - Clinics and Services 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Department General Funds 1989-1991 (Box 2)
    - Faculty
      - Alpern, Mathew (includes symposium and memorial) 1979-1996 (Box 2)
      - Green, Daniel G. Retirement Dinner and Book of Remembrances 2003 (includes photographs and a CD with photographs of Daniel G. Green's retirement dinner) (Box 2)
    - Eye Center Problems and General Issues 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Meetings 1981-1990 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Retreats
      - Faculty Retreats 1985-1992, 8 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Faculty Retreats 1979-1984 (Box 2)
    - Hospital Support (Funding Issues) 1992 (Box 2)
    - Medical School/Hospital Support 1987 (Box 2)
    - Operating Room Privileges 1979-1984 (Box 2)
    - Outpatient Satisfaction Survey 1986 (Box 2)
    - Pathology 1980-1997 (Box 2)
    - Photographs Undated (Box 2)
    - Research Committee 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Residency Review Committee 1995-1997 (Box 3)
    - Residents General Correspondence 1993-1998 (Box 3)
    - Reviews
      - Departmental Review 1987, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - External Review 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Skillman Clinic and General Ophthalmology 1992 (Box 3)
    - Strategic Planning 1990-1991, 1995, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Student Health Service University of Michigan; 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Taylor Lions Club Scholarship 1978-1989 (Box 3)
    - Training Grant 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Turner Geriatric Clinic 1980-1990 (Box 3)
    - Ultrasound 1990 (Box 3)
    - Veterans Administration Hospital 1978-1994, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Vivarium 1984-1992 (Box 3)
    - Warren, Larry (Hospital Administration) 1986-1994 (Box 3)
  - Paul Lichter Personal Files
    - Ophthalmology
      - Editorials and Material Relating to the journal 1986-1994 (Box 3)
      - Memos from Lichter and Congratulatory Letters 1986-1995 (Box 3)
    - Texas 1979 (Box 3)
  - W. K. Kellogg Eye Center
    - Planning
      - Auditorium 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - Auditorium Architectural Plans (Part B) 1982 (Box 4)
      - Base Plans Levels 1 and 2 June 5, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Equipment Proposal 1983 (Box 4)
      - Functional and Space Plan (Planning) 1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Functional and Space Program 1979 (Box 4)
      - Financial Analysis (Box 4)
      - Letters of Support Eye Center Planning 1979 (Box 4)
      - Map of Department Locations and Photograph of Model Undated (Box 4)
      - Memos re: Master Planning 1995 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Eye Center Interior Design Material 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Eye Center Part A Material 1983 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Eye Center Part B Material 1981-1984 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Financial Material 1984 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Planning Material 1979-1986 (Box 4)
      - Narrative Program for the Consolidation of Ophthalmologic Services at Parkview/Turner 1980, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Phase I Facilities Report of Audiovisual Systems Recommendations for the Eye Research Center Auditorium (Box 4)
      - Planning Eye Center 1977-1980 (Box 4)
      - Program Plans Part B undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Program Proposal for Consolidation of Ophthalmology Services at the Parkview/Turner Hospital Final Report December 1978 (Box 4)
      - Program Analysis for the Education and Research Building (Part B) 3/1981 (Box 4)
      - Robert Douglass Associates -- Interim Reports 1986, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Schematic Design Report for Part B (Research and Faculty Office Building) 1982 (Box 4)
    - Fundraising
      - Case for Support (E.C. Funding) Undated (Box 4)
      - Cost Figures 1981 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Fundraising Material 1978-1981 (Box 4)
      - Ways of Giving Brochure Undated (Box 4)
    - Construction
      - Certificate of Need 1977-1979 (Box 4)
      - Consolidation of Ophthalmology Parkview/Turner Hospital Part A Clinical Facilities 2/27/1981 (Box 5)
      - Consolidation of Ophthalmology W.K. Kellogg Eye Center Part B 1/1983 (Box 5)
      - Costs (Construction) 1980-1981 (Box 5)
      - Eye Center Construction Grant 1981-1986 (Box 5)
      - Eye Center Construction Grant National Eye Institute 1982, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Eye Center Construction Grant National Institutes of Health 5th Floor 1985 (Box 5)
      - Part A -- Parkview/Turner Eye Center Construction 1979-1982 (Box 5)
      - Part B -- Research/Education Building (Eye Center Construction) 1980-1981 (Box 5)
      - Meetings by Date 1980-1982 (includes Preliminary Budget Model -- University of Michigan Eye Center -- Part B, 12/12/1980 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous Construction Grants Material 1980-1983 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous Planning Material 1982-1984 (Box 5)
      - Preliminary Budget Model -- University of Michigan Eye Center Part B 12/12/1980 (Box 5)
    - Dedication
      - Alumni Day/Eye Center 1985 (Box 5)
      - Eye Center Dedication Committee 1984-1985 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous Eye Center Dedication Materials 1985 (includes Dedication Address given by Bradley R. Straatsma) (Box 5)
      - Straatsma, Bradley R. (includes Straatsma's Honorary Degree Nomination) 1984-1985 (Box 5)
      - Thanks Yous and Follow -- up 1985 (Box 5)
Related Material
Henderson, John W. The University of Michigan Department of Ophthalmology: A Proud Heritage, (Ann Arbor, Michigan: The Department of Ophthalmology, University of Michigan Medical School, 1986)
The Department of Ophthalmology and Visual Sciences at the University of Michigan, 1872-1999: a Heritage of Excellence, (Ann Arbor, Michigan, The Department. of Ophthalmology and Visual Sciences, University of Michigan, 1999).
Related holdings in the library include the records of the University of Michigan Medical School and the personal papers of John W. Henderson. For further information about the construction of the W.K. Kellogg Eye Center refer to the University Architect's Office (University of Michigan) records.